In this lesson, we'll
do a deep dive into
an advanced RAG technique, our
sentence window retrieval method. In
this method, we
retrieve based on smaller
sentences to better match
the relevant context, and
then synthesize based on
an expanded context window
around the sentence. Let's check
out how to set it up. First, some context.
The standard RAG pipeline uses
the same text chunk for both
embedding and synthesis. The issue
is that embedding and synthesis. The
issue
is that embedding-based retrieval typically
works well with smaller
chunks, whereas the LLM
needs more context and bigger chunks
to synthesize a good answer. What
sentence window retrieval does is
decouple the two a bit. We
first embed smaller chunks or sentences
and store them in
a vector database. We also add
context of the sentences that
occur before and after to
each chunk. During retrieval, we
retrieve the sentences that are
most relevant to the question with
a similarity search
and then replace
the sentence with a full surrounding
context. This allows us
to expand the context
that's actually fed to
the LLM in order to answer
the question. This notebook will introduce
the various components
needed to construct
a sentence window
retriever with Llama
Index. The various components will
be covered in detail.
At the end, Anupam will show you
how to experiment with parameters and
evaluation with TruEra.
This is the same
setup that you've used in the previous
lessons, so make sure to install
the relevant packages, such
as Llama Index and
Truelines eval. For this quick start, you'll
need an open AI key
similar to previous lessons. This
open AI key is used
for embeddings, LLMs, and
also the evaluation piece. Now
we set up and inspect
our documents to use for iteration
and experimentation. Similar to the first
lesson, we
encourage you to upload your
own PDF file as well.
As with before, we'll load in
the How to Build
a Career in AI eBook. It's
the same document as before. So we
see that it's a list of
documents, there are 41 pages,
the object schemas are document
object, and here is
some sample text from the first
page. The next piece is,
we'll merge these into a
single document because it helps
with overall text blending accuracy when
using more advanced
retrievers. Now let's
set up the
sentence window retrieval method, and
we'll go through how to set
this up more in
depth. We'll start with a window size
of 3 and a top K value
of 6. First, we'll import what we
call a sentence window node parser. The sentence window node
parser is an object that
will split a document into
individual sentences and then augment each
sentence chunk with the surrounding context
around that sentence.
Here we demonstrate
how the node
parser works with
a small example.
We see
that our text, which
has three sentences, gets
split into three nodes.
Each node contains a single
sentence with the metadata
containing a larger window around
the sentence. We'll
show what that metadata looks like
for the second
node right here. You see
that this metadata contains
the original sentence, but
also the sentence that occurred
before and after it.
We encourage you to
try out your own text too.
For instance, let's try something
like this. For this sample
text, let's take a look at the
surrounding metadata for the first node.
Since the window size is
3, we have two
additional adjacent nodes that
occur in front, and
of course none behind it because
it's the first node. So
we see that we have
the original sentence, or
hello, but also foobar
and cat dog. The next step is actually
build the index, and the
first thing
we'll do is a setup in
LLM. In this case,
we'll use OpenAI, specifically
GPT-355 Turbo, with a temperature
of 0.1. The next step is to
set up a service context object, which,
as a reminder, is
a wrapper object that contains all
the context needed for indexing,
including the AL1, embedding model, and
the node parser. Note
that the embedding model
that we specify is
the "bge small model,"
and we actually download and
run it locally from
HuggingFace. This is a compact,
fast, and accurate for its
size embedding model. We can also
use other embedding model. For instance,
a related model is "bge
large," which we have
in the commented-out code
below. The next step is the setup
of VectorStoreIndex with the source document.
Because we've
defined the node parser as part
of the service context, what this will
do is it will
take the source document,
transform it
into a series of sentences
augmented with surrounding contexts, and embed
it, and load it into
the VectorStore. We can save the
index to disk so that you
can load it
later without rebuilding it. If
you've already built the index, saved
it, and you don't want to rebuild it,
here is a handy
block of code that allows
you to load the index from the
existing file if it exists,
otherwise, it will build it.
The index is now built. The next step
is to set up
and run the query
engine. First, what we'll do
is we'll define what we
call a metadata replacement post-processor.
This takes a value stored in
the metadata and replaces a node text
with that value. And so this
is done after retrieving
the nodes and before sending
the nodes to the outline.
We'll first walk through
how this works. Using
the nodes we created with the sentence window
node parser, we can
test this post-processor. Note
that we made a backup of
the original nodes. Let's take a look
at the second node again. Great.
Now let's apply the post-processor
on top of these nodes. If
we now take a look
at the text of the second
node, we see that it's been replaced with a
full context, including the sentences that occurred
before and after the current node.
The next step is to add
the sentence transformer re-rank model. This takes
the query and retrieve
nodes and re-order the nodes in order
relevance using a
specialized model for the task. Generally,
you will make the initial similarity top
K larger, and then the
re-ranker will rescore the nodes and
return a smaller top N,
so filter out a
smaller set. An example
of a re-ranker is bge-re-ranker
based. This is a re-ranker
based on the bge embeddings.
This string represents the
model's name from HuggingFace, and
you can find more details on
the model from HuggingFace. Let's take
a look at how this re-ranker works. We'll
input some toy data and then see
how the re-ranker can actually re-rank
the initial set of nodes
to a new set of nodes. Let's
assume the original query is I
want a dog,
and the initial set of score nodes is
this is a
cat with a score of
0.6, and then this is a
dog with a score
of 0.4. Intuitively, you would expect
that the second node actually has a
higher score, so it matches
the query more. And so
that's where the re-ranker can
come in. Here, we see
the re-ranker properly surfaces the known about dogs
and gave it a high
score of irrelevance. Now let's apply this
to our actual query engine.
As mentioned earlier, we
want a larger similarity
top K than the top N
value we chose for the re-ranker. In
order to give the re-ranker
a fair chance at
surfacing the proper
information. We set the top K
equal to 6 and top N
equals to
2, which means that we first fetch the
six most similar
chunks using the sentence window
retrieval, and then we filter
for the top two most relevant chunks using
the sentence re-ranker. Now that we
have the full query
engine set up, let's run
through a basic example. Let's ask a
question over this dataset. What are the
keys to building a
career in AI? And
we get back to
response. We see that
the final response is that
the keys to building a
career in AI are learning foundational
technical skills, working on projects,
and finding a job. Now that
we have the sentence window query engine
in place, let's put everything together. We'll
put a lot of code
into this notebook cell, but
note that this is essentially the
same as the function
in the utils.BAAI file.
We have functions for building the sentence window
index that we showed
earlier in this notebook.
It consists of being
able to use the sentence
window node parser to extract
out sentences
from documents and augment it
with surrounding contexts. It contains
setting up the sentence context
or using the service
context object. It also
consists of setting up a vector
sort index, using the source documents
and the service context
containing the LLM embedding
model and node parser.
The second part of this is
actually getting the sentence window query
entered, which we
showed consists of
getting the sentence
window retriever, using
the metadata replacement post processor to
actually replace a
node with the surrounding
context, and then finally using
a re-ranking module to filter
for the top N results. We
combine all of
this using the as query intro
module. Let's first call build
sentence window index with
the source document, them, as
well as the save directory. And
then let's call the
second function to
get the sentence
window query engine. Great. Now you're
ready to experiment
with sentence window retrieval. In the
next section, Audit Prompt
will show you how to
actually run evaluations using the
sentence window retriever, so that you
can evaluate the results
and actually play
around the parameters and see
how that affects the performance of your
engine. After running through these examples, we
encourage you to add
your own questions and then
even define your own evaluation benchmarks
just to play around
with this and get
a sense of how everything works.
Thanks, Jerry. Now that you have set
up the sentence window retriever,
let's see how we can
evaluate it with the
RAG triad and compare
its performance to the
basic rag with experiment
tracking. Let us now see how
we can evaluate and
iterate on the sentence
window size parameter to
make the right trade-offs between
the evaluation metrics, or the
quality of the app, and the
cost of running the
application and evaluation. We
will gradually increase the
sentence window size
starting with 1, evaluate the
successive app versions
with TrueLens and the RAG triad,
track experiments to pick the best
sentence window size, and as
we go through this exercise, we will
want to note the trade-offs between token
usage or cost. As we increase
the window size, the token usage
and cost will go up, as in many
cases will context relevance. At the
same time, increasing the window
size in the beginning, we expect
will improve context relevance
and therefore will
also indirectly improve
groundedness. One of
the reasons for that
is when the retrieval step does
not produce sufficiently
relevant context, the
LLM in the completion step will
tend to fill in
those gaps by leveraging
its pre-existing knowledge from the
pre-training stage rather than explicitly
relying on the
retrieved pieces of
context. And this choice can result
in lower groundedness scores because recall
groundedness means components
of the final
response should be
traceable back to
the retrieved pieces of context. Consequently,
what we expect is
that as you keep increasing
your sentence window size,
context relevance will increase
up
to a certain point,
as will groundedness, and then
beyond that point,
we will see context relevance
either flatten out
or decrease, and
groundedness is likely going
to follow a similar
pattern as well. In
addition, there is also
a very interesting relationship between
context relevance and
groundedness that you
can see in
practice. When context relevance is low,
groundedness tends to be low
as well. This is because the LLM
will usually try to
fill in the gaps in the retrieved pieces
of context by leveraging
its knowledge from the
pre-training stage. This results
in a reduction in
groundedness, even if the answers actually
happen
to be quite relevant. As
context relevance increases, groundedness also
tends to increase up
to a certain point. But
if the context size becomes
too big, even if
the context relevance is
high, there could be a drop in
the groundedness because the
LLM can get overwhelmed
with contexts that are
too large and fall
back on its pre-existing knowledge base from the
training phase. Let us now
experiment with the sentence
window size. I will
walk you through a notebook
to load a few questions for
evaluation and then gradually increase the
sentence window size
and observe the
impact of that
on the RAG triad evaluation metrics.
First, we load a set of
pre-generated evaluation questions. And you can see here
some of these
questions from this list. Next, we run the
evaluations for each question in
that preloaded set of evaluation questions.
And then, with the true recorder
object, we record the
prompts, the responses, the intermediate
results of the application,
as well
as the evaluation
results, in the
true database. Let's now adjust the
sentence window size parameter and
look at the impact of that
on the different RAG triad evaluation
metrics. We will first reset the
true database. With this
code snippet, we set the sentence window
size to 1. You'll
notice that in this instruction. Everything else is
the
same as before. Then we set
the sentence window engine with the get
sentence window query engine associated with
this index. And next up, we
are ready to
set up the true recorder with
the sentence window size set to 1. And
this sets up the
definition of all the feedback functions for the
RAG triad, including answer relevance, context
relevance, and groundedness.
And now we
have everything set
up to
run the evaluations for the setup
with the sentence window
size set to 1.
Okay, that ran beautifully.
Now let's look at it in the
dashboard. You'll see that this
instruction brings up a locally hosted StreamLit app,
and you can click
on the link to
get to the StreamLit
app. So the app leader board
shows us the aggregate metrics for all
the 21 records that we ran
through and evaluated with TrueLens. The
average latency here is 4.57 seconds.
The total cost is about
two cents. Total number of tokens
processed is
about 9,000. And you can see the
evaluation metrics. The application
does reasonably well in answer
relevance and groundedness, but on context relevance,
it's quite poor.
Let's now drill
down and look at
the individual records that were
processed by the application and evaluated. If
I scroll to the right, I
can see some examples where the
application is not
doing so well on these metrics.
So let me pick
this row, and then
we can go deeper
and examine how it's
doing. So the question here is,
in the context of project
selection and execution, explain the difference between
ready-fire and ready-fire-aim approaches. Provide
examples where each approach
might be more beneficial.
You can see the overall
response here in detail from the
RAG. And then,
if you scroll
down, we can see the overall scores
for groundedness, context relevance,
and answer relevance. Two pieces of
context were retrieved in this example. And for
1 of the pieces
of retrieved
context, context relevance
is quite low. Let's
drill down into that example
and take a closer
look. What you'll see here
with this example is that the
piece of context is quite
small. Remember that we are using
a sentence window of size 1, which
means we have only added
1 sentence extra in the
beginning and 1 sentence extra
at the end around the retrieve
piece of context. And
that produces a fairly
small piece of context
that is missing out
on important information that
would make it relevant to
the question that was asked. Similarly,
if you look at groundedness, we
will see that
both of these
pieces have retrieved the sentences. In
the final summary, the
groundedness scores are quite low.
Let's pick the one
with the higher groundedness
score, which has a
bit more justification. And
if we look at this example,
what we will see is
there are a few sentences
here in the beginning for which
there is good supporting evidence in the
retrieved piece of context. And so the score here
is high. It's a score of
10 on a
scale of 0
to 10. But then for these
sentences down here, there wasn't supporting evidence, and
therefore the groundedness score is 0. Let's take a concrete example. Maybe
this one. It's saying it's often used
in situations where the cost
of execution is
relatively low and where the
ability to iterate and adapt
quickly is more important than upfront planning.
This does feel like a plausible
piece of text that could be
useful as part of the response
to the question. However, it wasn't
there in the retrieved
piece of context, so
it's not backed up
by any supporting evidence
in the retrieved context.
This could possibly have been
part of what the model had learned
during its training phase, where either
from the same document,
Andrew's document here on
career advice for AI,
or some other source
talking about the same
topic, the model may
have learned similar information.
But it's not grounded in that
it
is not, the sentence is not supported by
the retrieved piece of
context in this particular instance.
So this is a general issue
when the sentence
window is too small, that context relevance tends
to be low. And as a
consequence, groundedness also becomes low because
the LLM starts
making use of its pre-existing knowledge from its
training phase to start answering
questions instead of just relying on the
supplied context. Now that
I've shown you a
failure mode with sentence
windows set to one, I
want to walk
through a few
more steps to
see how the
metrics improve as
we change the sentence window size.
For the purpose of
going through the notebook
quickly, I'm going to reload the evaluation questions,
but in this instance, just set it to
the one question where
the model had problem, this particular
question, which we just
walked through with the sentence
window size set at 1. And then
I want to run this
through with the sentence
window size set to
3. This code snippet
is going to
set up the rag
with sentence window size
set up three, and also
set up the true recorder
for it. We now have
the definition of the feedback function
set up in addition
to the RAG, with
the sentence window set
at size 3. Next up,
we are going to
run the evaluations with that
eval for that particular
evaluation question that we
have looked through in
some detail with the
sentence window set through one, where we observe
the failure mode that has run successfully. Let's
now look at the results with
sentence window engine
set to three in the TruLens
dashboard. You can
see the results here, I ran
it on the one record. That
was the problematic record when
we looked at sentence
window size one. And
you can see a
huge increase in the context
relevance. It went up from 0.57
to 0.9. Now if I select the
app and look at
this example in some
more detail, let's now look
at the same question that
we looked at with sentence
window set at one. Now we
are at 3. Here's the full final response. Now
if you look at the
retrieved pieces of context, you'll notice
that this particular piece
of retrieved context is
similar to the one
that we had retrieved earlier
with sentence window set at size
1. But now it has
the expansion because of the
bigger sentence window size. For
this section, we'll see
that this context
got a context-relevant score of 0.9,
which is higher than the score
of 0.8 that the smaller context
had gotten earlier. And this example
shows that with an
expansion in the sentence window
size, even reasonably good
pieces of retrieved context can get even better.
Once the completion step is
done with these significantly better pieces of context,
the groundedness score goes
up quite a bit.
We'd see that by
finding supporting evidence across
these two pieces of highly
relevant context, the
groundedness score actually goes up all
the way to one. So
increasing the sentence
window size from
one to three led
to a substantial improvement
in the evaluation metrics of the RAG triad.
Both groundedness and
context relevance went up significantly, as
did answer relevance.
And now we can look
at sentence window set to five.
If you look
at the metrics here, a couple
of things to
observe. One is
the total tokens has gone up,
and this could have
an impact on the
cost if
you were to increase
the number of records. So
that's one of the trade-offs that
I mentioned earlier. As you increase the
sentence window size, it gets more
expensive because more tokens are being processed by
the LLMs during evaluation.
The other thing to observe is that while
context relevance, and answer relevance have
remained flat, groundedness has actually dropped with
the increase in the sentence
window size. And this can happen
after a certain point
because, as the
context size increases, the LLM can
get overwhelmed in
the completion step with too
much information. And in the
process of summarization,
it can start
introducing its own
pre-existing knowledge instead of just the
information in the
retrieved pieces of context.
So to wrap things up
here, it turns out that
as we gradually increase
the sentence window size
from 1 to 3 to
5, 3, the size of 3
is the best choice for us for
this particular evaluation.
And we see the increase in
context relevance and answer
relevance and groundedness as we go
from one to 3,
and then a reduction
or degradation in the
groundedness step with a further increase to a size of five.
As you are playing with the notebook, we
encourage you
to rerun it with
more records in these
two steps. Examine the
individual records which are causing problems for specific
metrics like context relevance or groundedness,
and get some intuition and build
some intuition around why the failure modes
are happening and what to do to
address them, and in
the next section, we
will look at another advanced
rack technique auto
merging to address
some of those
failure modes. Irrelevant
context can creep into
the final response, resulting in not
such great scores
in groundedness or answer relevance.